Guide to the Memory Project Oral History collection, 2009-2016 | 民间记忆计划口述史 RL.10171
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Jiangxi province | 江西省, 2014-2016
  - Pengtian Village | 抚州市广昌县彭田村, 2016
    - Yi Guixiang | 夷桂香, 2016
      Yi Guixiang (b. 1945) is a resident of Pengtian Village, Jiangxi Province. In this interview, Yi talks about the difficult time during the Great Famine when she was working at a mold factory. Since 1958, if the villagers did not work at the production team, they would not obtain any food. Since everyone was only assigned with two liangs of rice, the rice had to be cooked with bran, potato scrapes and others. Moreover, there was always a scramble at the canteen for the scarce supply of food. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      夷桂香1945年出生，是江西省抚州市广昌县彭田村村民。在这段口述中，夷老人回忆了大饥荒时的困难生活。从1958年开始，如果不去生产队里干活就没有饭吃，夷老人在磨具厂工作，赚取收入。当时一个人只能分到二两米，和糠、洋芋渣等调在一起烧成饭吃。去大食堂吃饭时如果不争着抢就经常吃不到饭。
    - Gao Wei | 高伟, 2016
      Gao Wei (b. 1946) is a resident of Pengtian Village, Jiangxi Province. In this interview, Gao talks about the life during the Great Leap Forward and the Great Famine. In Gao's opinion, most leaders and members of the local production team only focused on superficial political slogans and exaggerating production rather than putting real effort into farming, which led to reduced grain production and eventually the famine. The situation did not improve until the communal canteen was closed down. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      高伟1946年出生，是江西省抚州市广昌县彭田村村民。在这段口述中，高老人讲述了大跃进和大饥荒时期的生活。高老人认为，当时生产队经常弄虚作假，只会做表面功夫，实际干活种田时出工不出力，导致粮食减产，造成饥荒。情况直到大食堂解散以后情况才开始好转。
    - Zeng Lianying | 曾莲英, 2016
      Zeng Lianying (b. 1925) is a resident of Pengtian Village, Jiangxi Province. In this interview, Zeng talks about the life during the Great Famine when she was working at the production team. The workload was very heavy and overtime at night was very common. The famine was at its worst in 1960 and 1961 when each person could only be assigned with 2 liangs of rice everyday. Due to starvation, Zeng sometimes had to steal food. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      曾连英1925年出生，是江西省抚州市广昌县彭田村村民。在这段口述中曾老人讲述了大饥荒时期的生活。曾老人当时在生产队干活，工作辛苦，天天晚上还要加夜班。大饥荒最苦的是60年和61年，一个人只能分到二两米，饿得不行的时候曾老人还偷过饭吃。
    - Chen Jiumei | 陈九妹, 2016
      Chen Jiumei (b. 1950) is a resident of Pengtian Village, Jiangxi Province. Due to his lack of money in raising kids, Chen's birth father embezzled 200 Yuan and was therefore arrested. Chen was then raised up by her adoptive parents since she was 8 month old. In this interview, Chen talks about the life during the Great Famine. Although no one starved to death in her village, many people stole food because of hunger. However, if caught, the convicted would face severe punishment including fines of money, grains and work points and even going to jail. During that time, many people from other places went to Jiangxi Province to beg for food. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      陈九妹1950年出生，是江西省抚州市广昌县彭田村村民。陈老人的亲生父亲因为没钱养孩子，贪污了两百元被逮捕，于是陈老人在8个月大的时候就被养父母领养。在这段口述中，陈老人回忆了大饥荒时的经历。当时村里虽然没有饿死人，但因为挨饿不少人就去偷吃的，一旦被抓住惩罚很严重，扣钱扣粮扣工分，甚至会坐牢。那时候还有很多外地人来江西讨饭。
    - Zeng Guiying | 曾桂英, 2016
      Zeng Guiying (b. 1932) is a resident of Pengtian Village, Jiangxi Province. In this interview, Zeng recalls the life during the Great Famine. In 1957 when the communal canteen was established, every household's pots and stoves were confiscated. The famine started in 1958. With three members, Zeng's family was only assigned one jin of rice everyday. The over 200 people at the communal canteen had to scramble for the scarce supply of food at every meal. In fear of hurting the unborn babies, pregnant women did not dare to join them. Because Zeng was usually not strong enough to get her portion of food, she had to rely on the food her dad, who was the leader of the people's commune, saved for her. Because of starvation, many people stole food from others, ate daffodils and even river mud. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      曾桂英1932年出生，是江西省抚州市广昌县彭田村村民，在这段口述中，曾老人回忆了大饥荒时期的经历。1957年村里开始办大食堂，家里的锅炉都被收走。1958年开始挨饿，曾老人一家三口一天只能分一斤米。每次吃饭一个食堂二百多个人争抢粮食，怀孕的害怕压到小孩都不敢去。曾老人当时抢不到饭，只能靠当社长的父亲分她一点粮食。因为挨饿有人便去偷吃的，甚至吃河泥、水仙花等。
    - Li Zhenzhu | 李珍珠, 2016
      Li Zhenzhu (b. 1939) is a resident of Pengtian Village, Jiangxi Province. In this interview, Li recalls the life during the Great Famine. Li started chopping firewood and sold them at the canteen with her father since she was 7 years old. During the Great Famine, everyone could only obtain two liangs of rice. To fill the stomach, they had to eat potato and sweet potato scrapes, which were usually to dry to be swallowed. The situation did not improve until when the communal canteen was closed and when people could have their own farming lands. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      李珍珠1939年出生，是江西省抚州市广昌县彭田村村民。在这段口述中，李老人讲述了大饥荒时的生活。李老人7岁起就和父亲一起去砍柴、挑柴去食堂卖。大饥荒时一天只有二两米，不够就只能吃红薯渣、洋芋渣之类的，非常干，难以下咽。直到大食堂解散，人民可以分田种，生活才得以改善。
- Liaoning province | 辽宁省, 2010
  - Huanzidong Village | 沈阳市法库县獾子洞村, 2010
    Huanzidong Village is located in Faku County, Shenyang City, Liaoning Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Lin Tao.
    獾子洞村位于辽宁省沈阳市法库县。村民的录像采访人是林涛。
    - Lin Fuchen | 林福臣, 2010
      Lin Fuchen (b. 1936) is a resident of Huanzidong Village, Shenyang, Liaoning Province. In this interview, Lin recalls the life during the Great Famine. When there was a good harvest in 1958, the corns that were not consumed were wasted and directly buried in the field. Then from 1959 the Great Famine started. Lin was working at Sanjiazi Coal Mine where he was given 55 jins of grains each month. Although he did not starve, the work there was very hard. During that time many people starved to death on the street, but no one had the strength to bury the dead bodies. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      林福臣1936年出生，是沈阳市法库县獾子洞村村民。在这段口述中，林老人回忆了大饥荒时的生活。1958年大丰收时，吃不完的玉米棒子就直接埋地里浪费了，到了1959年就开始挨饿。林老人在三家煤矿工作，一个月给五十五斤粮食，但工作非常辛苦。当时不少人饿死在路边，但也没有人有力气去埋葬尸体。
    - Cui Suzhen | 崔素贞, 2010
      Cui Suzhen (b. 1931) is a resident of Huanzidong Village, Shenyang, Liaoning Province. In this interview, Cui recalls the life during the Great Famine. Cui was working at the town's clothing shop where she could earn work credits and eat at the canteen. Her husband was working in Haerbin, Heilongjiang Province. Because they only had one kid and her husband's parents to feed, the family did not starve too much during that time.
      崔素贞1931年出生，是沈阳市法库县獾子洞村村民。在这段口述中，崔老人回忆了大饥荒时期的生活。当时崔老人在城里的成衣铺工作，可以换工分，一天两顿都在食堂吃。崔老人的丈夫在哈尔滨工作，家里就一个孩子和公公婆婆，所以一家并没有太饿着。
    - Bai Xiuqing | 白秀清, 2010
      Bai Xiuqing (b. 1923) is a resident of Huanzidong Village, Shenyang, Liaoning Province. In this interview, Bai talks about her experience of feeding the eleven family members during the Great Famine. Bai's husband was the head cook at the production team, while Bai worked at home cooking and doing needlework. During the collectivization when every household had to hand in their food to the production team, Bai's family hided some at their place. As a result, they did not suffer too much during the Great Famine.
      白秀清1923年出生，是沈阳市法库县獾子洞村村民。在这段口述中，白老人回忆了大饥荒时期照顾家里十一口人吃喝的经历。白老人的丈夫在生产队当伙夫长，老人一个人在家烧饭做针线活。集体化的时候粮食都归生产队，白老人家偷存了点粮食，所以大饥荒时没太饿着。
    - Zhang Zhihua | 张志华, 2010
      Zhang Zhihua (b. 1946) is a resident of Huanzidong Village, Shenyang, Liaoning Province. In this interview, Zhang recalls the life during the Great Famine. There were people who fled to Huanzidong Village from Hebei Province, while many local villagers fled to the Great Northern Wilderness for the relatively sufficient foods there. Zhang also talks about several villagers who starved to death during the Great Famine. Niu Fengtian's grandpa starved to death during sleep the day before the Chinese New Year. Without a proper coffin and clothes, he was buried in a crate that was used to contain soybean oil. In addition, many people died of food poisoning because of eating wild herbs and tree leaves. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      张志华1946年出生，是沈阳市法库县獾子洞村村民。在这段口述中，张老人讲述了大饥荒时期的生活。当时獾子洞有从河北逃难过来的，当地也有不少人逃到粮食相对充足的北大荒去。张老人还回忆了几位饿死的村民，其中牛丰田的爷爷是在春节前一天睡觉时饿死的，当时没有棺材和新衣服埋葬死者，只能用裝豆油的木箱充当棺材。除了饿死，还有好多人因为吃野菜、树叶导致食物中毒而死。
    - Pan Zhenhua | 潘振华, 2010
      Pan Zhenhua (b. 1945) is a resident of Huanzidong Village, Shenyang, Liaoning Province. In this interview, Pan talks about the life during the Great Famine. Despite the reduced production, the cadres of the local production teams exaggerated the numbers in their report to the higher government for their own profit. As a result, the grains were taken to the higher level government and ordinary villagers had to starve. The situation was at its worst in 1960, when many people starved to death and corpses were put in cabinets due to the lack of coffins. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      潘振华1945年出生，是沈阳市法库县獾子洞村村民。在这段口述中，潘老人讲述了大饥荒时的经历。当时粮食减产，但生产队干部为了自己的利益向上级政府虚报收成，导致粮食都被上缴而百姓只能挨饿。60年情况最严重，好多人饿死，因为没有棺材，尸体只能用柜子装。
    - Yang Deshan | 杨德山, 2010
      Yang Deshan (b. 1934) is a resident of Huanzidong Village, Shenyang, Liaoning Province. In this interview, Yang talks about the life during the Great Famine. The communal canteen was established in 1958: everyone had to eat there and no one was allowed to cook at home. 1958 saw a very good harvest, yet people wasted a lot of food. 1960 saw a much reduced production and the country had to pay back the debt to the Soviet Union, the Great Famine started as a result. Yang was working as the warehouse keeper at the production team, so he could sneak out some food for his family to keep them from starving. However, many villagers starved to death, especially the elderly and the sick. There were foods in the granary but because it was the government's grain reserves in case of war, the government did not open the granary even though people were starving. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      杨德山1934年出生，是沈阳市法库县獾子洞村村民。在这段口述中，杨老人回忆了大饥荒时的生活。1958年成立大食堂，不许各家烧火，要求人们都上食堂吃饭。1958年大丰收粮食多，不少人都浪费粮食，到60年粮食就减产了，加上要还苏联外债，饥荒开始了。杨老人因为是在生产队当保管长，可以拿点粮食回家，所以他们家没太挨饿，但好多村民都饿死，尤其是老人和病人。当时粮库虽然有粮食，但因为是国家的储备粮，所以并没有发放给挨饿的百姓。
    - Yang Zhizhong | 杨志忠, 2010
      Yang Zhizhong (b. 1934) is a resident of Huanzidong Village, Shenyang, Liaoning Province. In this interview, Yang talks about his life during and after the Great Famine. Back then Yang's family was at his wife's hometown, Tongliao, Inner Mongolia. Foods were sufficient there, so Yang's family did not starve much. Yang was working on a livestock farm, but in order to make extra money, he hunted wild birds during his spare time.
      杨志忠1934年出生，是沈阳市法库县獾子洞村村民。在这段口述中，杨老人回忆了大饥荒时期及之后的生活。当时杨老人在他老伴老家内蒙古省通辽市，那边粮食充足，老人一家并没挨饿。杨老人在牧场工作，为了多挣点外快，他还在业余时打野鸟卖钱。
    - Yin Tingzhi | 尹廷芝, 2010
      Yin Tingzhi (b. 1929) is a resident of Huanzidong Village, Shenyang, Liaoning Province. In this interview, Yin talks about her experience of fleeing to the Great Northern Wilderness where foods were relatively sufficient during the Great Famine. In order to make money for the trip, Yin's family sold the wooden parts of their house to the Sanjiazi Coal Mine, but they had to keep the land because everyone was starving and no one wanted it. In the Great Northern Wilderness, Yin's husband worked for the local production team. The family of six had to sleep on a small bed extended by a piece of plank. After six months, because it was too cold there and her daughter was old enough to get married, Yin's family moved back to Huanzidong Village. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      尹廷芝1929年出生，是沈阳市法库县獾子洞村村民。在这段口述中，尹老人回忆了大饥荒时期逃难到粮食相对充足的北大荒的经历。为了凑够路费，尹老人一家把房子的木结构卖给三家子煤矿，但因为饥荒没人需要地皮，他们只能自己留下。到了北大荒后尹老人的丈夫在生产队工作，一家六口人就睡在一个小炕上，一边还拿木板接着。待了半年以后因为北大荒太冷，女儿也到了该结婚的年纪，尹老人全家又搬回了獾子洞。
    - Yin Tingxiang | 尹廷祥, 2010
      Yin Tingxiang (b. 1942) is a resident of Huanzidong Village, Shenyang, Liaoning Province. In this interview, Yin recalls the life during the Great Famine. Many people were starving to death and the dead bodies were stacked up on the streets. Yin was still at school during that time. However, because of the famine, they did not have any class but all went out to dig wild herbs and tree barks for extra sustenance. Many people fled to Jilin and Heilongjiang Province because there were more foods there.
      尹廷祥1942年出生，是沈阳市法库县獾子洞村村民。在这段口述中，尹老人回忆了大饥荒时期的生活。那时村里饿死不少人，尸体堆得很高。尹老人当时还在上学，但因为大家都挨饿，学校也不上课，大家都去挖野菜吃树皮。好多人都逃到吉林、黑龙江等粮食相对充足的地方。
    - Yang Wanxiang | 杨万祥, 2010
      Yang Wanxiang (b. 1922) is a resident of Huanzidong Village, Shenyang, Liaoning Province. In this interview, Yang recalls the life during the Great Famine. Yang was working as the supervisor of the village's production team. In 1959, everyone was still eating at the communal canteen, but starting from 1960 when the famine was at its worst, people had to eat at home. Many starved to death in that year. The situation began to improve in 1961. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      杨万祥1922年出生，是辽宁省沈阳市法库县獾子洞村村民。在这段口述中，杨万祥回忆了大饥荒时期的生活。杨老师当时是村里生产队的指导员。村里1959年还在大食堂吃饭，到了1960年就回家里吃饭，那一年最困难，村里饿死了不少人。情况直到1961年才有所好转。
- Shandong province | 山东省, 2009-2013
  - Chenjia Village | 滨州市阳信县商店镇陈家村, 2010
    Chenjia Village is located in Yangxin County, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Zou Xueping.
    陈家村位于山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇。村民的录像采访人是邹雪平。
    - Gao Junrong | 高俊荣, 2010
    - Si Jinguan | 司金官, 2010
      Si Jinguan (b.1935) lives in Chenjia Village, Shangdian Town, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. In this interview, Si recalls life during the Great Famine. She and her husband were in their 20s, but the hunger weakened them so much that they coulnd't do any work. They ate all kinds of leaves and wild herbs. Several people starved to death in the village.
      司金官1935年出生，是山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇陈家村人。在这段口述中，司老人回忆了大饥荒时期的生活。因为挨饿，那时才二十几岁的她和他丈夫都干不动活，各种树叶和野菜都拿来吃。村里饿死了好几个人。
    - Zhang Peiying | 张佩英, 2010
    - Wang Xiuying | 王秀英, 2010
  - Guanzhuang Village | 滨州市阳信县劳店乡官庄村, 2010
    Guanzhuang Village is located in Yangxin County, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Zou Xueping.
    官庄村位于山东省滨州市阳信县劳店乡。村民的录像采访人是邹雪平。
    - Wang Xiangrong | 王香荣, 2010
  - Xiaoyin Village | 滨州市阳信县商店镇小殷村, 2010
    Xiaoyin Village is located in Yangxin County, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Zou Xueping.
    小殷村位于山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇。村民的录像采访人是邹雪平。
    - Li Hongying | 李红英, 2010
      Li Hongying (b. 1941) is a resident of Xiaoyin Village, Shangdian Town, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. In this interview, Li remembers life during the Great Famine. Beginning in 1958, people worked together in the field (called 'large formation combat'). They were starving and looking everywhere for things to eat. Only later did people get some food at People's Commune canteen. That year, four people in her family starved to death.
      李红英1941年出生，是山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇小殷村的村民。在这段口述中，李老人回忆了大饥荒时的生活。1958年开展'大兵团作战'，人们挨着饿在地里干活，四处找东西吃。之后吃上食堂才分到些食物。她家里那一年饿死了四口人。
    - Yin Huizhang | 殷会章, 2010
      Yin Huizhang (b. 1939) is a resident of Xiaoyin Village, Shangdian Town, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. In this interview, Yin remembers life during the Great Famine. He used to be the barn keeper of the Production Team, yet he didn't see grains for six months between 1959 and 1960. Later, people could get half jin (250 grams) of food each day after working. In the worst year, more than 800 people, about half of the population in Shawo Village and Guanzhuang Village either starved to death or left (migrated to the Northeast, re-married, etc.).
      殷会章1939年出生，是山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇小殷村的村民。在这段口述中，殷老人回忆了大饥荒时的生活。他当时是生产队的粮食保管，1959年到1960年期间有六个月没见过粮食。在此之后人们干了活能在食堂领半斤粮食。那一年沙窝村和官庄村饿死的和离开的（逃去东北、改嫁等等）总共有八百多人，约原人口的一半。
  - Zoujia Village | 滨州市阳信县商店镇邹家村, 2009-2013
    Zoujia Village is located in Yangxin County, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Zou Xueping.
    邹家村位于山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇。村民的录像采访人是邹雪平。
    - Zou Shoutang | 邹寿堂, 2012
    - Zou Peishan | 邹佩珊, 2012
    - Li Guiying | 李桂英, 2010
      Li Guiying (b.1925) is a resident of Zoujia Village, Shangdian Town, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. In this interview, Li recalls her experience during the Great Famine. At that time, people were so starved that they were too weak to do anything, and they ate whatever they could find. Many people in the village starved to death.
      李桂英1925年出生，是山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇邹家村的村民。在这段口述中，李老人回忆了大饥荒期间的经历。那时人们饿得做什么都没力气，也找来各种东西吃。村里饿死得人不少。
    - Chen Fengying | 陈凤英, 2010
      Chen Fengying (b. 1937) was born in Zoujia Village, Shangdian Town, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. In this interview, Chen talks about what she ate during the Great Famine. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      陈凤英1937年出生于山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇邹家村。 在这段口述中，陈老人讲述了她在大饥荒期间吃的食物。
    - Fu Yu'e | 付玉娥, 2010
      Fu Yu'e (b.1926) is a resident of Zoujia Village, Shangdian Town, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. In this interview, Fu recalls her experience during the Great Famine. When People's Commune canteen started, she had a daughter, and she gave birth to her younger son in 1960. In order to save food for her children, she was often so starved that she could barely move.
      付玉娥1926年出生，是山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇邹家村的村民。在这段口述中，付老人回忆了大饥荒期间的经历。吃食堂时她已经有了个女儿，1960年生下了小儿子。为了省下粮食给孩子吃，她常常饿得动弹不得。
    - Du Fengying | 杜凤英, 2010
      Du Fengying (b. 1935) was born in Zoujia Village, Shangdian Town, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. In this interview, Du recalls her experience at home and at People's Commune canteen during the Great Famine. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      杜凤英1935年出生于山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇邹家村。在这段口述中，杜老人回忆了大饥荒期间她在家里和公社食堂的经历。
    - Gao Yurong | 高玉荣, 2010
      Gao Yurong (b. 1941) was born in Zoujia Village, Shangdian Town, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. Four of Gao's family members died during the Great Famine. In this interview, she talks about People's Commune canteen, and those who starved to death, particularly her mother-in-law and grandmother. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      高玉荣1941年出生于山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇邹家村。她家在大饥荒期间死了四口人。 在这段口述中，高老人说起了公社食堂和饿死的人，特别是她的婆婆和奶奶。
    - Li Xiyao | 李喜瑶, 2010
    - Zou Dengwu | 邹登武, 2010
    - Zhang Xuerong | 张学荣, 2010
    - Lv Junrong | 吕俊荣, 2010
      Lv Junrong (b. 1946) was born in Zoujia Village, Shangdian Town, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. In this oral history, Lv remembers how people suffered and what they ate during the Great Famine.
      吕俊荣1946年出生于山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇邹家村。在这段口述历史中， 吕老人回忆了大饥荒期间人们受的磨难和吃的食物。
    - Zou Dengke | 邹登科, 2010
      Zou Dengke (b. 1938) was born in Zoujia Village, Shangdian Town, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. In this interview, Zou recalls life during the Great Famine. In the beginning, Zou and his wife tried everything to earn money for food, saving most food for their children. After the People's Commune canteen was established, he could get food after carrying coal every day, and life became slightly better. Although he saw food get wasted and knows that the famine was not a natural disaster, Zou still insist that the famine is not caused by Chairman Mao's policy, but the cadres at the local level.
      邹登科1938年出生于山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇邹家村。在这段口述中，邹老人回忆了大饥荒时期的生活。饥荒刚开始的时候，他和妻子用各种办法挣钱换吃的，还把吃的省給孩子们。食堂办起来后，他每天去推碳能分到粮食，生活稍微好转了些。虽然邹登科看见过好好的粮食被糟蹋，也知道饥荒不是自然灾害，他却强调说这不是因为毛主席的政策，而是下边的官有问题。
    - Zou Ailin | 邹爱玲, 2012
      Zou Ailing (b.1941) was born in Zoujia Village, Shangdian Town, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. She is Zou Quantang's older sister. In this interview, Zou clearly remembers the starvation she experienced during the Great Famine. When the 'Five Winds' first started, people had nothing to eat and the People's Commune canteen was not set up; Zou has eaten anything she could find. During the famine, her mother and two uncles all starved to death. The situation improved slightly later and people could eat sweet potato after earning work points, but many children starved to death.
      邹爱玲1941年出生于山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇邹家村。她是邹全堂的姐姐。在这段口述中，邹老人讲述了她记忆深刻的大饥荒期间挨饿的经历。刚开始'刮五风'时，人们没有粮食，集体食堂也没有建立，邹爱玲什么都找来吃过。她的大伯，二伯和母亲都在这段时间饿死了。后来稍有好转，挣了工分能吃地瓜，但饿死了不少孩子。
    - Zou Jinping | 邹金萍, 2010-2011
      Zou Jinping (b. 1941) is a resident of Zoujia Village, Shangdian Town, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. In this interview, Zou describes life during the Great Famine when there was severe shortage of food, even cooking utensils.
      邹金萍1941年出生，是山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇邹家村的村民。在这段口述中， 邹老人描述了大饥荒期间食物和炊具都匮乏的生活。
    - Zou Peiji | 邹佩吉, 2010-2012
      Zou Peiji (b. 1944) was born in Zoujia Village, Shangdian Town, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. In this interview, Zou recalls the difficult time during the Great Famine, when two people died every day in the village and nobody worked in the field. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      邹佩吉1944年出生于山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇邹家村。在这段口述中，邹老人回忆了三年饥荒最困难的时期；村子里每天饿死两个人，地里也没人干活。
    - Li Yutian | 李玉田, 2010
      Li Yutian (b. 1940) was born in Zoujia Village, Shangdian Town, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. He went to Boshan to work at a steel furnace in 1958. In this interview, Li talks about what and how he ate during the Great Famine.
      李玉田1940年出生于山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇邹家村。1958年他去了博山炼钢铁。在这段口述中，李老人讲述了他在大饥荒期间吃了什么，怎么吃的。
    - Li Xintian | 李鑫田, 2010
      Li Xintian (b.1934) is a resident of Zoujia Village, Shangdian Town, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. In this interview, Li talks about his experience during the Great Famine. The most bitters days started in the later half of 1959, when People's Commune Canteen had no food. Not only were grains extremely lacking, but both men and women also had to go dredging and ditching, leaving the elder and children at home. The starving people were forced to eat anything they could find. More than eighty people in his village starved to death, including his mother and two grandmothers. Life became a little better in the later half of 1961, when eight liang of grains was offered.
      李鑫田1934年出生，是山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇邹家村的村民。在这段口述中，李老人讲述了大饥荒时期的经历。最苦是1959年的下半年，食堂都吃不上了。不仅分的粮食远远不够吃，还不管男女都要到出去挖河挖沟，只剩下老人和孩子在家。挨饿的人们被逼得什么都吃。村里饿死了八十几个人，包括他的母亲和两个奶奶。1961年下半年开始按'八大两供应'，生活才好了一些。
    - Zhao Changfeng | 赵长凤, 2010
      Zhao Changfeng (b. 1941) is a resident of Zoujia Village, Shangdian Town, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. In this interview, Zhao recalls her experience during the Great Famine. When she was seventeen, she went begging with her mother; due to his lame leg, her father stayed home and made bamboo baskets in exchange of food. Later, she went begging in another county with a girl called Xiao Huan, walking long distances on foot and very scared of people's dogs. At that time, it was fortunate to get even just a little food from others. At 18 years old, she worked in the field for work points and ate anything she could find.
      赵长凤1941年出生，是山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇邹家村的村民。在这段口述中，赵老人回忆了大饥荒期间的经历。她17岁时和母亲一起去要饭，父亲因为腿瘸待在家里编箩筐换粮食。后来她也和另一个姑娘小寰一起走着去别的县要饭，最怕别人家里的狗。那时偶尔要到几口干粮已经觉得不错。18岁的时候在地里干活，饿得什么都找来吃。
    - Zhang Xirong | 张希荣, 2009-2012
      Zhang Xirong (b. 1936) was born in Zoujia Village, Shangdian Town, Binzhou City, Shandong Province. In this interview, Zhang talks about eating at People's Commune canteen and at home during the Great Famine. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      张希荣1936年出生于山东省滨州市阳信县商店镇邹家村。 在这段口述中， 张老人描述了大饥荒期间在公社食堂和家里吃饭的情况。
    - Wu Fenge | 吴凤娥, 2010
    - Wang Xiuqin | 王秀芹, 2010